<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rites of the Christian church further defended in answer to the appeal of Dr. Wake : with a letter to Mr. Hill ... on the account of the Municipium ecclesiasticum, as also an answer / by Sam. Hill ...</title>
            <author>Hill, Samuel, 1648-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5805</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12705664</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12705664</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66017</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66017)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 357:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rites of the Christian church further defended in answer to the appeal of Dr. Wake : with a letter to Mr. Hill ... on the account of the Municipium ecclesiasticum, as also an answer / by Sam. Hill ...</title>
                  <author>Hill, Samuel, 1648-1716.</author>
                  <author>N. N.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 59 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Sold by the book sellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A letter to Mr. Hill" signed: N.N.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Trinity College Library, Cambridge, England.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wake, William, 1657-1737. --  Sermons. --  Selections. --  1690.</term>
               <term>Hill, Samuel, 1648-1716. --  Municipium ecclesiasticum.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66017:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66017:1"/>
            <p>THE RITES OF THE Chriſtian Church further defended, In Anſwer to the Appeal of Dr. <hi>WAKE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Letter to Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> Rector of <hi>Kilmington,</hi> on the account of THE <hi>Municipium Eccleſiaſticum.</hi> As alſo an Anſwer.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Sam. Hill</hi> Rector of <hi>Kilmington.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 18.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If I have ſpoken evil, bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the evil; but if well, why ſmiteſt thou me?</p>
            </q>
            <p>Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:66017:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66017:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER Written to Mr. <hi>HILL</hi> on the account of the <hi>Municipium Eccleſiaſticum,</hi> With the Anſwer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TAking it for granted that you are the Author of <hi>Municipium Eecleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticum,</hi> and that you will think your ſelf obliged to remove thoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66017:3"/>Charges laid upon you in your Adverſary's Appeal, I think fit on ſo tickliſh a Point, to offer you ſome Conſiderations, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, in my Opinion, to allay the Prejudices that ſeem to lye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you.</p>
            <p>For firſt of all, There are ſome that conceive you to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Letter to a Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation man,</hi> and therein to have thrown a needleſs Bone of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in a time of great Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies under the late Plot and War, with very ſuſpicious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon the Greateſt in the Government; and conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your daring Attempt not long before upon a formidable Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, your Enemies ſtick not to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66017:3"/>repreſent you as a Man of Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diary Humours, a Prejudice ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eaſie to take among Strangers and Perſons diſaffected, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in a ſoft Age diſſolved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Courtſhip and Careſſes. On which account I ſhould with ſubmiſſion think it not expedient to avert thoſe Miſconſtructions, by ſetting forth Truth under its fair and equal Reaſons for the generous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, and this with your Name ſet to take off the Reproach of a Libel fixed on it. The part that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to the intrinſick Merits and Subſtance of the Cauſe, appears in the Appeal it ſelf, which you know beſt how to treat; and therefore I do not pretend to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66017:4"/>you thereupon; but wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you all Succeſs, Reward, and Happineſs for your many Pious, Hazardous, and — Labours for this poor Church, I ſubſcribe,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>New Atlant, <date>Feb. <hi>24. 1697</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Yours Entirely N. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer_to_letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66017:4"/>
            <head>The Anſwer.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce you were not pleaſed to let me know you, nor where to return Thanks for ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing an Office, yet ſince you have given ſuch Uſeful Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, you have fixed me in a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod how to appear on this Appeal, about which I was before very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious and undetermined; for now I think it the moſt proper way for me to give you an Epiſtolary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my ſenſe in this matter; which being ſent by the Preſs, will find you in your Secrecy, and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66017:5"/>at once both you and the Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial World againſt ſuch Surmiſes which ſuch an Adventure muſt needs draw upon it.</p>
            <p>Know you then that we are ſo far from being the firſt ſtarter of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, that after all poſſible inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiveneſs we have not been able ſo much as to gueſs at him, nor are we at all concern'd in thoſe (whether real or pretended) reflections, at which his adverſaries are all ſo fired. And to be free with you and the world, if the paſſages taxed, did in truth deſign reproach, his own conſcience ought to ſmite him, &amp; will one time or other do ſo ſeverely, if for nothing elſe, yet for the <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>falſe Colours:</hi> but ſince his language carries in it an apparent zeal and veneration for all authorities now in being, and particularly hopes for vengeance on thoſe that reflect upon His Majeſty to create a Jealouſie with his people, we think his Oppon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents have no warrant from any rules of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66017:5"/>Juſtice and Charity to pronounce him a reviler ſo abſolutely as they have done; and if God, who ſearcheth the hearts, finds him to be as intentionally innocent as his words are, then theſe Men have brought that guilt of male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicence on themſelves with which they now load him. So that herein they ſeem not to have conſidered our Saviours precepts againſt Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs, as much as how to gratifie their own malice or ambitions. But as to what really concerns us, we are not very ſolicitous what partial men ſay of us, becauſe no prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations in the world can inhibit their malice, and therefore in what we are accountable to God alone, to him alone will we reſerve our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, being contented to leave with the world theſe arguments of our integrity, that though we could have laid trains of aſſentation in order to advancement, by avoiding all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſting writings, and by bending our capacities to ſerve the preſent Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66017:6"/>in Officious Treatiſes and fulſom Dedications, and had proſpects fair enough before us to have led us into ſuch temptation, yet have we never ſlained our conciſence or our pen by any ſuch little and illiberal Artifices, but have always choſen rather to pleaſe God in the Cauſe of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith and Church againſt all unjuſt diſpleaſures of Men, than to be ſacrilegiouſly guilty in corrupting or betraying thoſe Divine Principles and Conſtitutions: and if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that any perſon, eſpecially of the ſacred Robe, can be offended at us for ſerving the Cauſe of Chriſtianity at the Expence of our powers, and at the loſs of all our worldly Intereſts, we can only recommend them to Gods mercy, and in the mean time condole the ſtate of the Church in that there are ſome in her that are more concerned for her promotions than her fundamentals.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:66017:6"/>
            <p> But though Integrity is under no ſuch great Obligations to ſtand in awe of the delicate or cenſorious world in order to any internal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ſatisfaction, yet that its deſigns may be more ſerviceable to the holy Ends propoſed, we ſhall not grudge to ſhew what juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons there were to oppoſe the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and Principles of this Doctor tending ſo openly and violently to the ruine of the Eccleſiaſtical Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Conſtitutions. It is too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately known to all conſidering and religious Perſons, how much the ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant Advances of Hereſie and new Schemes of Chriſtian Faith created in the Church a deſire of a free Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, to correct theſe Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies by the methods uſed in ſuch caſes through all Ages. And we wiſh we could not ſay that the Intereſt of the Criminals hath found a party againſt the general appetite and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Church, inſpired with a Spite from the dead againſt the lower
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66017:7"/>houſe of Convocation, not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated till they can hope to introduce thereinto a number and majority ready and ſequacious in the execution of their purpoſes. In which unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and irreligious Project they club in with all the Atheiſts, Infidels and Sectaries of the Nation, a ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Inſtance wherof we have in this Doctor, who has for Complices in this Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note n="*" place="margin">Author of the Eſſay concerning the power of the Magiſtrate and Rites of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in matters of Religion, in his Poſtſcript concerning the Letter to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation Man.</note> one profligate Anti-chriſtian Infidel, and foul-mouth reviler of the whole Church of God through all Ages, and egregiouſly of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in this laſt Age, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with which not only his Darlings the Sectaries (his ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able tools to Irreligion and Scepticiſm) but even the Papiſts, (againſt whom however he inveighs ſufficiently) nay the very Heathens are very Lambs and Saints; and another Anti-Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66017:7"/>and Anti-Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demical Lawyer of the ſame bran,<note n="†" place="margin">Author of the Letter to a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and this diſcernibly enough, tho' not ſo raging, but more tect and ſly in his Methods of Miſchief. Of this fraternity all along have been thoſe worthy Monitors of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation at their laſt Seſſion, and thoſe raging Calumniators of it that malign it ever ſince, becauſe not waxen enough for ſome Mens Impreſſions. Which ſawcy Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if offered to the Guardians of our Civil Liberties, would have brought the Adventurers under the Zeal and Inquiſition of the State, while the grand depoſitory of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity is ſecurely vilified and uſed as our Lord and Maſter, which is however the greateſt honour in the ſight of God, though otherwiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by malicious and vexatious Men. And yet while open Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies do us this diſhonour, we can the better bear it, but to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66017:8"/>trayed up to the ſcorn of all our Enemies by thoſe that eat the ſame bread, and drink of the ſame cup, is that which calls back the ſaddeſt Example of horrour in this kind to our Remembrance and Reſentments. All which being conſidered, will eaſily juſtifie the <hi>Municipium Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticum</hi> from the ſuſpicion of a cauſeleſs and incendiary Undertaking. Nor can we think that even the Civil State will conceive any offence at it, ſince they that undermine the Authority of the Church in Spirituals, overturn the Superſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the Magiſtrates Intereſt in the Civil Conduct of Religion. For no Man can think that a Secular Authority has a more Interiour Right in Eccleſiaſticals than the Church its ſelf, and therefore the illuſtrious Author of the Eſſay above-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, has with the ſame hand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed all Civil as well as Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical power in matters religious; which when the State ſhall be at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66017:8"/>leiſure to recollect, it will no doubt be jealous for its own Authority in the moſt important Concern, and when it ſhall appear that this is overturned by deſtroying the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the Church, what will be thought of thoſe Church-men that have ſupplied theſe Caitiffs with Match and Powder? And if the Church ſhall not diſclaim ſuch Proditors of her own, how can the State think that we will be true and truſty to the Civil Rights and Liberties of the Nation, that are ſo negligent and prodigal of our own, and hereby at once become the publick ſcorn and ſcandal?</p>
            <p>But if we are not to ſollicit the cares or ſentiments of the State, as to their own Matters; yet we think we may be permitted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and correct the Inſolencies of Clergy-men, making all poſſible ſail to preferment by a ſpiteful and contemptuous Carriage toward the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66017:9"/>ſupreameſt powers in the Church, who can traduce the uſe, wiſdom, and gravity of all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Synods in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,<note n="(1.)" place="margin">Author of Chriſt. Prine. p. <hi>306.</hi>
               </note> by Reflections that will deſtroy as much the Authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,<note n="(2.)" place="margin">
                  <hi>p</hi> 317.</note> not ſparing any as far as appears of the great <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Synods<note n="(3.)" place="margin">
                  <hi>p</hi> 307.</note> for the ſake of thoſe that were corrupted purely on the Court Intereſt, which he fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently conceals; who in the times of Popery ſcouts the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, even when oppoſing the avarice of the Pope,<note n="(4.)" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 195, 197, 198.</note> as well as for aſſerting their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities againſt the King upon the Authority and Injunctions of the Pope,<note n="(5.)" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 205, 350 <hi>to</hi> 356. <hi>and</hi> 298 <hi>to</hi> 303.</note> while yet his own hiſtorical Deduction aſcribes the firſt Introduction of the Papal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to the Acts and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of Kings againſt the Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Power of the Church, on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66017:9"/>which however he paſſes no cenſure,<note n="(6.)" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 178, 179, 181, 182, 186, 187, 194, 195, 197, 199, 203.</note> above the bare rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of fact and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation of Weakneſs; who beſide all this is more Satyrical upon the Reputation of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, even now in a ſtate of Reformation, and vaſt Learning, and Experience,<note n="(7.)" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 42, 43, 82, 112, 270, 271, 272, 297, 316, 317, 320, 325, 329, 330, 337, 343. <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal. p.</hi> 121.</note> as if they were the moſt peeviſh, untractable, ſpiteful, imprudent and dangerous Societies to Kings and States, that can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, in no wiſe to be truſted, but under. Guards and Irons; who can when no provocation is given, not only vilify his Adverſary, and even at the ſame time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a tenderneſs in this point,<note n="(8.)" place="margin">Dedi. p <hi>3, 4.</hi> Pref. p. vij. Book p. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>261, 262, 296, 304, 305, 339, 345, 346, 347.</hi> Pref. to Appeal. p. xxiij. xxiv. compared with the whole malicious Book.</note> but even take occaſion, where none of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered it ſelf, to render the preſent Clergy, or a great part of them, odious, as Men quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relſome
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66017:10"/>and barbarous<note n="(9)" place="margin">Author of Princ. Pref. p. vij. viij. Book p. <hi>332, 333, 334.</hi>
               </note> hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally perjured for the ſake of their Preferment, and yet Seditious againſt the Government<note n="(10)" place="margin">p. <hi>349, 355.</hi> Dedic. to Appeal. p. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> to which they have Sworn and ſome aſſociated; as if he were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the fall of thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Clergy-men, who have ſunk under falſe Notions and Principles of Allegiance, but had an appetite to exaſperate the Publick unto more diſcriminating and more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting Teſts in order to a more Numerous and Tragical Evacuation of Churches; for certainly that Spite and Wickedneſs of ſurmiſe againſt ſuch a ſuppoſed miſchievous Party, yet remaining in the Boſom and Communion of the Church, can import no leſs; that ſo we might have an Hiſtory of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in all things conformable, or in no wiſe inſeriour to that of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66017:10"/>
               <hi>Scotland.</hi> Hence is it that this Inhumanity of Deſign, as well as Corruption of Principles, has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it ſelf to the juſt ſcorn and deteſtation of the Clergy of this Kingdom, and there is no Charge in the <hi>Municipium,</hi> equal to the Malignity of the Project.</p>
            <p>And having thus given you (as I think) ſufficient Reaſons, why ſuch a malicious and calumnious Book ſhould be refuted, we think little need be ſaid for the <hi>Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium</hi>'s being nameleſs to purge it from the imputation of Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; For if a Book be good, that concealment cannot, impeach it; if it be naught, the prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Name does not ſo much excuſe the Libel as atteſt and ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate the Impudence; the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of which the <hi>Municipium</hi> was willing to decline with thoſe who would be ſure or likely to reproach the Author with that Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſion,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66017:11"/>and if to avoid this Rock he has daſhed upon the other, he muſt bear his Fortune as well as he can, and commit his Cauſe to him that judgeth righteouſly.</p>
            <p>From theſe Provocations, come we now to the Appeal it ſelf, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both the Exteriour Pretence, as well as the Interiour Weight and Subſtance of it, that ſo the Readers may be able, by eaſie and obvious Views, to diſcern its Pertinency and its Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Then we muſt begin with the Pretence ſet forth in the Title of the Appeal, which runs thus; <hi>An Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all the true Members of the Church of</hi> England <hi>in behalf of the King's Eccleſiaſtical Supremacy, as by Law Eſtabliſhed; by our Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions approved; by our moſt Eminent Biſhops and Clergy men Stated, and Defended; againſt both the Popiſh and Fanatical Oppoſers of it.</hi> So that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66017:11"/>herein four things preſent themſelves to our Conſideration.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Of what form this Book is; namely, that 'tis an Appeal.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To whom 'tis offered; to all true Members of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, In what Cauſe; in the behalf of the King's Supremacy, as by Law Eſtabliſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Againſt whom; and they are both Popiſh and Fanatick Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers. The Title Page being thus ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into parts, is accordingly in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>Now Firſt, Appeals in Law are forms of action againſt ſome Illegal Proceſs or Sentence of an Inferiour Judge, which he, ſuppoſing himſelf to have ſuſtained by the <hi>Municipium,</hi> appeals to all true Members of this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66017:12"/>Church, as more righteous and equal Judges. So that if he alledge any ſuch <hi>Gravamen</hi> or <hi>falſe Judgment,</hi> and prove it by the exhibition or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the acts, in all ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances he ought to carry, otherwiſe to loſe his Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Judges appealed to are all true Members of this Church; on which the <hi>Party appellate</hi> is in ſuſpence; not that he ſuſpects ſuch Judges, but knows not whom the <hi>Appellant</hi> intends. For it appears by other repetitions<note n="*" place="margin">App. p. 117. lin. 3, 4.</note>, that 'tis a Critical and Diſtinctive Character from falſe Members in this Doctors deſign, tho' he has left them as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcernible for want of a particular Note as the Subject of Infallibility in the Roman Church. For firſt, the Deprived Clergy claim this as their Peculiar Honour merited by their Cauſe and Sufferings: And in the next place, among the undeprived
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66017:12"/>this Drs, <hi>Acumen</hi> has ſmelt out a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of perjured railing Incendiary Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, that are ſetting up for a third Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ap. p. 3.</note>, namely, thoſe that are for the <hi>Municipium,</hi> which to his utter grief he finds to be the Body of the Clergy every where, even home to his Doors. Now theſe are dangerous Judges for the Dr. to truſt ſuch an Appeal with. So that in the third place the Myſtery is, that thoſe few of his Party that are againſt all Divine Authorities in the Church, are his ſecure Judges, his allowed Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and then indeed we and the Church too is undone, if we decline not ſuch Judges. Either therefore let him ſhew us our very Judges, or be content to carry the Appeal to the Apoſtles and Fathers of the Church Catholick, and we will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily joyn with him, if need be.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:66017:13"/>
            <p> Thirdly, The Cauſe or Matter in Appeal is here pretended to be the King's Eccleſiaſtical Supremacy as by Law Eſtabliſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But how this comes to be the Subject of an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal <hi>againſt</hi> the <hi>Municipium,</hi> and <hi>for</hi> his former Book, I cannot conceive. 'Tis true, the <hi>Letter to a Convocation-man</hi> after his Aſſertion of the Divine Right of Synods, endeavours, not to deny the King's Eccleſiaſtical Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, but under that, to aſſert a like Legal Liberty to Convocations as to Parliaments, in which latter part upon our Legal Eſtabliſhment the <hi>Minicipium</hi> did not concern it ſelf. But being diſſatisfied with the Drs. denial of the Sacred Powers, and with that unlimited Syſtem of Regal Authorities aſcribed to all Chriſtian Princes on the meer Right of their Magiſtracy, which are truly collected into nine Aphoriſms out of the Drs. Book in the 108 and 109 pages of the <hi>Municipium,</hi> it undertakes the refutation of theſe his general Maxims
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66017:13"/>So that the Dr. has appealed in a Cauſe in which we never proſecuted him. So that except it appear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on production of ſayings in the <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicipium,</hi> that the particular Legal Eſtabliſhment of our King's Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Supremacy is impaired or impeached therein, it ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted by our Judges; and this is what we ſtand to in this Appeal, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating that according to the Title of the former Book (now ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from all Princes to ours only) he ought to have laid his Appeal in behalf of the Authority of Chriſtian Princes [in general and ſimply] over their Eccleſiaſtical Synods; as by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſtated and aſſerted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is, againſt the Divine Right of Synods in the Church, and for thoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of all Chriſtian Princes ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med up in thoſe nine Aphoriſms. This then is a defect in the very Title and Pretence of Body of it he yet if really in the Body of it he has made out theſe his Maxims for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66017:14"/>all Chriſtian Princes, we will be content that the <hi>Municipium</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as ſeverely as the Doctor deſires.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Adverſaries againſt whom he Appeals, are all Popiſh and Fanatical Oppoſers of the Kings Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Supremacy; (for ſo the interpunctation of the <hi>Semicolons</hi> after three Participles, does deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his intention, that herein he may not ſhuffle) but all along the Appeal you find no Book reflected on but the <hi>Municipium;</hi> So that this ſeemed a pretty Artifice, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Adverſary under hated and ignominious Characters, tho' he knows him as far from thoſe Imputations, as any Man in <hi>England.</hi> For as he knows the Catholick Ballance againſt Popery, and the Diſſertation <hi>de Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteratu</hi> againſt Franticks, to have been as unanſwered, and perhaps as unanſwerable by thoſe Parties, as the <hi>Municipium</hi> is by himſelf, ſo the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66017:14"/>very <hi>Municipium</hi> it ſelf aſſerting the Divine Rights of the Epiſcopal Hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archy does herein at once as well oppoſe the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> as the <hi>Genevian</hi> or <hi>Scotch</hi> Conſiſtories. So that if this part of the Title be ſincere, we are not the Perſon againſt whom this Appeal is brought; if it be calumnious, it will affect no Mans Integrity or Reputation but his own. But to gratify the pretty <hi>Caprice</hi> for once, let us be Popiſh or Fanatick, or any other Exotick or Invidious Name; what then will the Conſequence be? Namely this, that then we may fairly decline his Judges the True Members of this <hi>Church;</hi> and his Authorities therein, namely, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, Canons and Laws, and the Sayings of her Biſhops and Doctors; It being an unequal thing that we ſhould be concluded by prejudicate Parties, eſpecially conſidering that all the Fanaticks, who deny the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Supremacy, as much as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66017:15"/>Papiſts; and as equally the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities owned in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> are tolerated in the whole Profeſſion of their Fanaticiſms againſt this Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy and theſe Authorities, even by the Supream Civil Powers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>And conſequently if the Doctor has not proved his Authorities pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in this Church, to be good upon Prior and more Eminent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, ſuch as are thoſe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Common Reaſon, and the Antient Church Catholick, to which the <hi>Municipium</hi> yields and refers it ſelf, and ought ſo to do; but has left the Arguments of the <hi>Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium</hi> with no other anſwer but this, that they are contrary to the Principles eſtabliſh'd, and Notions receiv'd in this Church, what does he elſe but betray his Church to contempt, and confeſs that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments in the <hi>Municipium</hi> have overthrown the Senſes of this Church
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66017:15"/>by Scripture, Reaſon and Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Antiquity, on which the Dr. was not able to reply one word. To ſuch Abſurdities, indeliberate Rages uſe to betray Men.</p>
            <p>From the Titular Form of this Appeal, proceed we now to the inner Part and Body thereof, if perhaps he has therein diſcharged himſelf from the Convictions of the <hi>Municipium,</hi> which challenged him of two dangerous Principles; one for diſowning the Church to be a Society, or to be endued with any Synodical Authorities till In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into the State;<note n="*" place="margin">Auth. of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti. Princ.</hi> p. 265, 266, 267. <hi>cit. ap. Munic. Eccleſ.</hi> p. 2, 3, 4.</note> the other in aſſerting to all Chriſtian Princes, on the meer Right of their Magiſtracy all thoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities in and over Synods, Collected into the Nine Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms. p. 108, 109. of the <hi>Munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:66017:16"/>
            <p> To refute the firſt Principle of the Doctor, the <hi>Municipium</hi> ſpends its Eight firſt Chapters upon Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Scripture, and Antiquity, and ſhews him, that by this Principle of his he unwittingly denies the Unity of the Catholick Church, to which (ſo civil and benign are Men when baffled) the Learned Doctor replies not one word. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we muſt challenge him to Anſwer thoſe Eight Chapters effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, or we muſt conclude upon his perſiſtence in this Errour, that he will obſtinately renounce one Article of his Creed, and one part of his Baptiſmal Vow and Liturgy, the 8th, 19th, 20th and 34th Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our Religion, to which he has given aſſent in all his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, the penal Conſequences of which, even in this World, he may remember from thoſe objected to the <hi>Municipium</hi> in this pretended Appeal. In the mean, however, here
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66017:16"/>being no defence made againſt theſe Eight Chapters, for the Churches Divine Powers, we crave Right and Juſtice of our Judges, and deſire a clear diſmiſſion as to this Article, becauſe this Synodical and Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Authority in the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Civil Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration is aſſerted alſo in the Teſtimonies and Authorities,<note place="margin">1 Can. of 1640. Appeal. p. 8. Dr. <hi>Heylin. ibid. p.</hi> 88, 89. Biſhop <hi>Taylor.</hi> p. 97. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Parker,</hi> p. 98, 100. Dr. <hi>Falkner</hi> 103, 104. Dr. <hi>Barrow,</hi> p. 160.</note> produced in this Appeal, as well as by our 20th and 34th Article of Religion, and 139th Canon.</p>
            <p>So much then, and ſo little for the firſt Matter charged on the Dr. by the <hi>Municipium;</hi> come we now to enquire what he has done for his Nine Aphoriſms, which we muſt here tranſcribe with a little Verbal Correction and Expunction of the word <hi>[Canons]</hi> in the 7th, becauſe he pretends himſelf wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it, tho' he that conſiders his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66017:17"/>89th page, referred to in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin of the <hi>Municipium,</hi> will find that the word <hi>[Conſtitutions]</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the ſame with <hi>[Canons]</hi> and that every where elſe he Aſſigns a far greater Power over Canons, than a bare Suſpenſion of their Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, which yet he neither diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owns, nor dares to diſown. <hi>Municip. Eccleſ.</hi> Chap. 9. § 4. Now the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Dr. chiefly conſiſts in theſe Aphoriſms;</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <list>
                     <item>1.<note n="1" place="margin">p. 14, 41, 48, 76.</note> 
                        <hi>That under the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate the Church has no inherent Right or Authority to Convene in Synods, but what it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives from the expreſs Conceſſion of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Prince.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2.<note n="2" place="margin">p. 84, 85, 136 to 139, 289, 38, 286.</note> 
                        <hi>For that all Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods are but of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to the Prince, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66017:17"/>entirely in his hands; and ſo</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Not any to be ſent to the Synod, but ſuch as he ſhall allow; nor</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4.<note n="4" place="margin">p. 79 to 83, 106, 107, 110, 112, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 132.</note> 
                        <hi>When convened; to Sit, Debate, Propoſe, Deliberate, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, or Decree any Matter of Doctrine, or Diſcipline whatſoever;</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5.<note n="5" place="margin">p. 44, 53, 54, 71.</note> 
                        <hi>Nor in any Form, Method or Manner whatſoever, ſave what the Prince admits; and that</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6.<note n="6" place="margin">p. 81 to 86, 133.</note> 
                        <hi>The Prince may Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, Annihilate, or Alter all their Acts, and Procedures, or as many of them as he pleaſes; and</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:66017:18"/>
                     <item> 7.<note n="7" place="margin">p. 85 to [89] 125, 126.</note> 
                        <hi>Suſpend the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all or any of their [Conſtitutions and] Sentences;</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8.<note n="8" place="margin">p. 288.</note> 
                        <hi>The Authority of their Acts being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely and only. his; and laſtly, that</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>9.<note n="9" place="margin">p. 77 to 79</note> 
                        <hi>No Synod hath Right to diſſolve it ſelf without the Kings Licenſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe Aphoriſms he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſupport ſometimes, and rarely by interſperſed Intimations or hints of Reaſon, but profeſſedly by Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>As to his Reaſons, they are all anſwered in the Ninth Chapter of the <hi>Municipium,</hi> to which he has not given one Syllable in order to Refutation.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:66017:18"/>
            <p> The Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for a ſecond Part; only in preparation thereunto, the Tenth Chapter does examine what Legal Grounds there can be to juſtifie Regal Interpoſitions in Synodical Concerns, without which they muſt be taken for injurious Acts of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; which <hi>Chapter</hi> lays down ſuch Principles, as will deſtroy all Pleas of general Preſcription or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification from thoſe Acts of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which go beyond the Lines of Regal Authority allowed in the <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nictpium,</hi> p. 105, 106, 123, 124. where a particular <hi>Contract</hi> with a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Prince,</hi> cannot be proved or well preſumed. But this is nothing to the general Right of all Princes, for whom the Doctor would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe from ſome Facts recorded in Hiſtory, which cannot preſume a <hi>Contract</hi> for all Princes with all <hi>Churches</hi> univerſally.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:66017:19"/>
            <p> Now to this tenth Chapter, laid as a bar and prejudice to all his Inferences, for the general Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency of all Kings in Spirituals, what replies the Doctor? Truly to be Uniform, and all of a Piece, not one Syllable or Gape; But only ſhifts and juggles that he has ſaid no more, <q>
                  <hi>And defended no other Authority in the Prince</hi> (meaning our King) <hi>than what both he and we, and every other Clergy-man of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>have ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared our Aſſent to, and are obliged to our Power to maintain.</hi>
               </q> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Pref. to App. p. vj, vij. 39 Can. Firſt Can.</note> But this is nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for the Queſtion is not <hi>what our Kings peculiar Prerogative is, as King of</hi> England <hi>in Vertue of our Laws,</hi> but <hi>what is the general Right of all Chriſtian Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigns as ſuch;</hi> and hereof we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a proof, that <hi>we have Aſſented to all thoſe Aphoriſms, and are
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66017:19"/>bound to defend them to our utmoſt;</hi> If this can be done, 'twill be a good Argument againſt us (though not with all the World that have made no ſuch Subſcriptions) not ſo much to aſſert Truth, as to muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle our Mouths: But even as to our own King, we deſire that it may be proved accordingly to the ſecond Aphoriſm, <q>
                  <hi>That all our Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods are but of Counſel to the Prince, and entirely in his hands;</hi>
               </q> and that, as in Aphor. 8. <q>
                  <hi>The Authority of their Acts is entirely and only his;</hi>
               </q> and moreover that, <q>
                  <hi>That we have ſubſcribed an Aſſent and Promiſe to defend it.</hi>
               </q> This is not yet done, and ſo we yet are in no danger from this part of the Appeal. But when Men are in the vein of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications, their Strains are more Airy and Rapturous, and in ſuch perhaps we may find ſomething more appoſite and daring. Now Dedic. to App. p. 3. he calls his a Cauſe, <q>
                  <hi>In which not only the Church
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:66017:20"/>of</hi> England, <hi>but the Church Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, ever ſince the Civil Powers, have become Chriſtian, is concerned together with her. The Authority he plead for, in behalf of our Kings being no other than what the moſt famous Biſhops and Councils of the Church, have given to their Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now this will reduce the Diſpute to a ſhort Iſſue; Let there be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction made of the moſt famous Biſhops and Councils of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, under Chriſtian Princes, aſſerting theſe Nine Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms of Eccleſiaſtical Authority, to all ſuch Princes on the ſole Right of their Magiſtracy, and we will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver up the <hi>Municipium</hi> to the Flames, and the Author to the moſt penitential Humiliations. It is not done in the former Book, 'tis not attempted in this Appeal; nay we have produced his own Contradictions in the moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:66017:20"/>Inſtances of ſuch Supremacy,<note n="*" place="margin">Munic: Eccl. p. 160, 166, 167, 168, 169, 172, 173, 175, 176</note> againſt theſe Infinite and Arbitrary Prerogatives, to many of which Remarks he has ſaid nothing, and ſo own'd them juſt, and to ſuch as he has excepted againſt, we ſhall ſhew his exceptions frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and cauſeleſs in due Place. And ſo as to all that was proper Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for Appeal in the <hi>Municipium,</hi> he has produced nothing to excuſe, much leſs to juſtifie his Cauſe and Principles, and ſo we humbly crave and hope for a diſmiſſion in this Second Part of the Controverſie alſo.</p>
            <p>But theſe Informations of ours, in this Cauſe of Appeal, though ſo very clear and undeniable, will be apt to leave the World under an amazement, that a Man ſhould Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal in a Cauſe, and make ſuch loud Clamours, and yet really not offer one pertinent Syllable for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66017:21"/>'tis ſo odd, ſo ſtrange a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, that the World will hardly believe their own Eyes. What, hath he made no Anſwer to any one Charge or Imputation at all? This is an hard Saying, who can believe? Who can bear it? Now to ſatisfie the World, the truth is, he appealed not in the Cauſe on which he was charged, nor made any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence thereof, but in a Cauſe of our own Kings Engliſh and Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Supremacy, for which the <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicipium</hi> never touched him. As to the merits of the Cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is none the leaſt defence made; and the whole conſidered as a formal Appeal, is a perfect and entire Impertinence. But whereas the <hi>Municipium</hi> taxed him, not only for the dangerous falſity of his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, but with ſeveral perſonal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertencies, Abſurdities, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions; ſome of theſe ſtrokes he has endeavoured to evade, which though Excentrick to the Pretended
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66017:21"/>or Real Matter in Appeal, ſhall have their due Examination, tho' we confeſs 'tis a very ſickly and unprofitable Labour, that muſt be imployed in winnowing ſuch Trifles.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And firſt of all the <hi>Munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium</hi> is blamed for four times<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Municip. Eccl.</hi> p. 6, 8.49, 55,</note> Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Definition of a Synod as unaccurate, whereas he never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it for a proper Definition, but plainly enough diſcovered his Senſe of it to be otherwiſe, tho' yet it had been a fit Companion for our as unaccurate a Definition. <hi>Pref.</hi> to <hi>App.</hi> p. xx.</p>
            <p>To which we Anſwer, That the Words appeared to us as a Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, on which an Argument was to be raiſed, concerning the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> Conference, for a Regal Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy over Synods, elſe how could it be deemed a Cavil, if it were no Synod, to alledge that it
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66017:22"/>was none; and ſo to reject it as an Impertinence? To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe does he call it <hi>a Meeting of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons on an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Affair, or ſuch an Aſſembly under Imperial Authority, as may juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the like Imperial Authority over any other of the like kind</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Auth. of Prin. p. 60.</note> if real and proper Synods were of another kind? What then, are proper Synods <hi>Meetings of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons on an Eccleſiaſtical Affair,</hi> or are they not? Or are they <hi>like</hi> or <hi>unlike</hi> to the <hi>Carthage</hi> Conference? It cannot be denied that Synods are ſuch Meetings; and if <hi>Miniſters</hi> had been ſet inſtead of <hi>Perſons,</hi> it had been an accurate Definition enough. Then again if they are <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> to the <hi>Carthage</hi> Conference, and that in their <hi>Synodical Form,</hi> the Inſtance of that Conference was idle and frivolous; if <hi>like,</hi> as he ſays, then the Deſcription thereof was intended for definitive. And
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66017:22"/>'tis falſe that the Doctor in the ſame place diſowned it to be a <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod,</hi> but having laboured to evince it to be ſo, yet waves urging it too much upon his cavilling Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and pretends to alledge others which were unqueſtionably proper Synods. But the main ſting in the <hi>Municipium</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">p. 7, 8.</note> the Doctor conceals, namely, that he had allowed thoſe huddles of Chriſtians running together in conſult under Alien Powers, to be proper <hi>Synods</hi> without <hi>Authority,</hi> from which abſurdity this Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Synod, tho' (as it ſeems) deſigned to comprehend all ſuch Cabals, could not defend him.</p>
            <p>And further yet, to ſhew his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated Inadvertency about the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> Conference, let it be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, That he ſays that Synods con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of the ſame kind of Perſons, as the <hi>Carthage</hi> Conference did,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66017:23"/>and about the like Affairs;<note n="*" place="margin">Auth. of Prin. p. 60. Pref. to App. p. xx.</note> How then can this be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned a Synod? But the truth is, tho' they met on the like Affairs, yet they did not conſiſt of the like <hi>Perſons.</hi> For in <hi>Ganonical Synods</hi> all the <hi>Members</hi> are to be <hi>Catholick,</hi> but the King and his Arians that carried all by force were not ſo, and conſequently were not <hi>Perſons Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> nor qualified with any Authority Regal or Canonical to Act under pretence of Authority, and ſo 'twas an induſtrious Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence to alledge it in Plea for Authority. But whereas he recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates on the Unaccurateneſs of our Definition, (p. 49.) we challenge him (tho' it be but a ſmall Pique) with all his skill to detect it, and we will readily own it, and thank him for the diſcovery.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:66017:23"/> 2. He complains of being falſe quoted in the 100 and 101 pages, and more injuriouſly, p. 109. of the <hi>Municipium. Pref.</hi> to <hi>App.</hi> p. xviij.</p>
            <p>To which we Anſwer, as to the 100 and 101 pages, That 'tis a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny, and refers to the ſaid pages; and as to the 109 page, we have above accounted for it in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction again of the Doctors A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſms; and the moſt that can be made of it, is an harmleſs In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertency; (<hi>quod temen non fate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur,</hi> &amp;c.) and if our Judges pleaſe to cenſure it for ſuch, we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with the Judgment, without any further Appeal.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That page 160, in the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Council of <hi>Ariminum</hi>'s ſelf-diſſolution, diſtinction is not made between his Hiſtorical Relation and his own Senſe thereof, which does not condemn that Act of the Council. <hi>Pref</hi> to <hi>App.</hi> p. 19.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:66017:24"/>
            <p> To which we Anſwer, that he is rightly repreſented, for he ſet a Rule Abſolute againſt the Self-Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of Synods, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves or exceptions; which muſt then <hi>ipſo facto</hi> condemn that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure or Concluſion of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Ariminum</hi> related immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon the Rule; and he brings moreover the Emperors diſguſt at that Diſſolution as an affront, a great Affront put upon him, and as a Corroboration to his Rule againſt that Act of the Council, as alſo his ſuggeſtion, That <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Valentinian</hi> took more care than to be ſo tricked or affronted, by the Council of <hi>Epheſus;</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">p. 77.</note> The ſame right he again aſſerts to Princes, againſt Self-Diſſolution of Synods;<note n="*" place="margin">p. 78.</note> and then finally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes,<note n="‖" place="margin">p. 79.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Duty of all Synods, as they are Convened by the Princes Authority, ſo to tarry till they have
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:66017:24"/>the ſame Authority for their Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</hi>
               </q> And if all this does not import a ſenſe againſt the Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Council of <hi>Arminium,</hi> we know not what can, We are ſure no man could think other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from the Precedents and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents in this Relation. But ſince he is now ſo candid as to ſuppoſe that theſe Fathers had good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for their unlicenſed Receſs, and ſo will not pretend at this diſtance, and under ſo much ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of their Motives, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them, we mightily applaud this forced Ingenuity; (if ſuch a Vertue can be forced) but then withall we muſt engage him ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther totally to expunge, or elſe to qualify his Rule herein with Exceptions for extraordinary Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That p. 166. He is unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged with Contradictions in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66017:25"/>Arguments from matter of Fact; See <hi>Pref.</hi> to <hi>App.</hi> p. xxj.</p>
            <p>To which we anſwer negative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Diſtinction of <hi>Regularity</hi> of the more <hi>antient</hi> Age, and the <hi>Irregularity</hi> of the <hi>later</hi> Ages, ſet in the Preface to the Appeal, not appearing in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Book.<note n="*" place="margin">p. 295, 296.</note> For he never uſed the Method of proving Imperial Acts <hi>Regular,</hi> by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring them with, or juſtifying them by any produced Rule or Principle; but he only produces their Acts to aſſert their Right. Now if ſuch bare Facts <hi>argue</hi> or legally <hi>preſume</hi> Right, without any other apparent Rule of Right, why ſhould not ſuch Facts publickly uſed in Synod by the Clergy, without Royal Licenſe, or Rebuke, or any Rule to the contrary then apparent, (as there is none alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the pages above noted) be as good Arguments for the Right
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66017:25"/>of the Liberty Synodically uſed without exception? Now ſince the Doctor ſet no Rules againſt that Liberty of Synods in the above noted Pages, then 'tis too late to hale them in now, ſo as to charge the Remark made upon him herein for injurious. And if a Man compares pag. 295. with pag. 112. he will conclude, that the <hi>Letter to a Convocation-Man</hi> argued fairly and ſtrongly for that Right of Liberty,<note n="‖" place="margin">Letter to a Conv. M. <hi>p. 58.</hi>
               </note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we can ſuppoſe that the Kings then had no better eſteem of their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods than as a pack of dangerous Villains, whom no Laws could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain, without Guards and Jay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors over them; which every one knows was not the common ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion againſt the Clergy in thoſe times.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:66017:26"/> 4. That pag. 167. He is unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taxed for an abſurd or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictious Relation of <hi>Genſtentines</hi> Words. <hi>Pref.</hi> to <hi>App.</hi> pag. xxj, xxij.</p>
            <p>To which we anſwer. That here the Doctor notoriouſly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges words of Remark that are not in the <hi>Municipium,</hi> contrary to Senſe as well as the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Intention, for 'tis not remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thoſe his Words, That <hi>Princes have nothing to do in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of Synods,</hi> for the <hi>Munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium</hi> aſſorts the contrary of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> in Right and Fact.) But the Remark is, <q>That this Saying is directly againſt that univerſal Right and Authority in Synods Eccleſiaſtical (Capitulated by us into nine Aphoriſms) given by the Doctor to all Princes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> and this Remark is immutably true, and uncapable of Impeachment.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:66017:26"/> 5. That pag. 168. the Remark of Contradiction upon the Saying of <hi>Socrates</hi> is injurious; <hi>Pref.</hi> to <hi>App.</hi> p. xxij.</p>
            <p>To which we Anſwer, That as the Words are in the <hi>Municipium,</hi> the charge is evidently True and Juſt, and we deſire our Judges to view the Columns; and to note firſt, That the Doctor leaves out the word <hi>[uſually]</hi> to repreſent the Senſe, that no leſſer Councils were called by Emperours, which is no part of the Intention, but only that leſſer Councils <hi>commonly</hi> were not, as appears alſo, <hi>Municip.</hi> p. 132. and this is proved by us, of four Synods out of the Doctor himſelf, in the place complained of, though the Doctor paſſes it over in ſilence to beguile his Reader.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:66017:27"/> 6. That pag. 169. he is inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly charged with Contradiction, in aſſerting the Right of <hi>Godly</hi> Princes in Convening Synods, and yet aſſerting the Churches Right herein under <hi>ill</hi> ones. <hi>Pref.</hi> to <hi>App.</hi> p. xxij. xxiij.</p>
            <p>To which we Anſwer, That the Contradiction in the Columns, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears undeniable, there being no diſtinction in his words between <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil</hi> Princes, that <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for,</hi> or <hi>neglect</hi> the Church, and for confirmation hereof, we refer alſo to the following Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, in which lies the moſt convictive force and evidence of the Charge.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible pretenſible matter of Appeal; as to his Principles againſt the Churches Divine Rights of Synods, and for his unlimited Domination
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66017:27"/>of all Princes in Eccleſiaſticals, he has not offered one word in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to all or any one Argument or Saying in the <hi>Municipium;</hi> and of 15 Inſtances of Abſurdity or Contradiction, he has excepted but at ſix, confeſſing thereby all the reſt to be juſt upon his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; and what ſorry Defences he has made on theſe ſix poor Heads of Complaint, we ſuppoſe our Judges muſt have needs ſeen, had we offered them no Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but now we ſuppoſe none is ſo blind, either through paſſion or ignorance, but muſt needs ſee the poor languiſhing Doctor utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enervated, and deſtitute of all Pretences for his Appeal.</p>
            <p>But be it ſo, the Doctor is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved however not to dye unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged; but if he had no Cauſe of <hi>Appeal,</hi> he will pretend one of <hi>Recrimination;</hi> that the Author of the <hi>Municipium</hi> has condemned our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:66017:28"/>Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitution under the Kings Supremacy, and called it Oppreſſive, aſſerted Divine Rights againſt it, and reflected againſt K. <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII. his Convocation and Parliaments, declared the Church to be out of the Kings Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſo he may pronounce him out of the Boſom of the Church, and advance a Croiſade for an holy Rebellion againſt him; by which this Impious Author is Perjured againſt his Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, hath renounced the 37th Article, broken the firſt, ſecond, twelveth, and other Canons of the Church, and ſo incurred deprivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by his Biſhop, without preſent Revocation of his Errors, and is excommunicate <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> not to be forgiven by an inferior Hand, but that of the Arch-Biſhop, upon Repentance and publick Revocation of his Wicked and Anabaptiſtical Errors; And to aggravate his Crime, he has done this againſt the Senſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:66017:28"/>of the greateſt Biſhops and Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Church, from whom the Doctor has brought many Citations.</p>
            <p>This is indeed a Thunder as loud as brute, and we require a proof as exact as what is judicial and convictive, and we are ſure he can never produce it. We can be Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before God and Man, that the Author of the <hi>Municipium</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves the 37th. Article, has vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olated no Cannon, nor Oath againſt the Eccleſiaſtical Supremacy owned and to be owned by the Church, according to allowed Rules of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation; which do not require from us a Sanctification of all our Acts in <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII's Reign, upon which I have reflected no more than what undeniable Hiſtory warrants; in which there are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:66017:29"/>
            <p> And for the Good he did, we owe him no thanks, for that he did it for ſelf or evil Ends, he Perſecuted at once both Papiſts and Proteſtants, and at laſt he and his Vicar General died Papiſts, and to that Church we leave them. We owe under God all true Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to the Memory of Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> for our Reformation; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her Injunctions, Orders, and Articles we have committed no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>We declaim againſt that Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation which the Doctor arrogates to all Princes, whether claimed by Devolution or Occupation; for as to Contract none ſuch can be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for all Princes, though there can with us for our Kings Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives; but on this we have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver paſt any Cenſure, even where occaſion preſented it ſelf, but ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended our Opinion, leaving the Judgement of our Original as well
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:66017:29"/>as ſubſequent Contracts herein to God the Judge of all; p. 136, 155, 176, nay, we make the Kings Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification and Concurrence neceſſary to give a Civil Force to Acts Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, p. 166, 175, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject all Perſons, Eccleſiaſtical as well as Temporal, to the Civil Sword for obſtinate and evil Doing, without any Exemption on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Prieſthood; pag. 105, 120, 125. without any ſeditious Reſiſtance of the Supreme Legiſlative Powers, or their Miniſters under Legal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, for that ſuch Powers are unaccountable to any Domeſtick Tribunal, and uncontroulable by the Subject, pag. 5.100 101, 106, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as to our particular Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to his preſent Majeſty, beſide our Honour aſſigned him in our Preface, we ſuppoſe the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Abiathar,</hi> and the <hi>Debate on the Juſtice and Piety of the Preſent Conſtitution</hi> may ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:66017:30"/>it as much at leaſt, as any of the Doctors falſe Services, for which he has obtained a good part of his paſt aims, and thinks his preſent attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as pledges of greater, while we have done our Duty to the King without intuition of reward, which we know we had once obſtructed by our Duty toward God, and have now done ſo again in oppoſing this Doctor.</p>
            <p>And therefore being not at all concerned at his ſanguinary Rages, we do ſtill renew to him the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Concluſions of our firſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and do not deſpair, after ſome Years Cooling and Meditation, but that he will alſo be of our Mind.</p>
            <p>As to what he has alledged out of the Worthies of our Church, there are very few Paſſages that are contrary to our Sentiments; and moſt are founded upon Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Hiſtory, and therefore we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:66017:30"/>ſhall prorogue their Examination to the ſecond Part, as they ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly offer themſelves at their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Inſtances; and then by Gods bleſſing, if not the Doctor, yet the diſintereſted part of the World, may receive ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>To conclude the whole; the Sum of our Senſe herein is, That the Church alone and by her ſelf, where the Chriſtian Prince will not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, (as that he may lawfully refuſe) has a Divine Right of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodical Authority in Canons and Sentences purely Eccleſiaſtical, and this the Doctor is forced to grant; but if the King and the Church Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract for Eſtabliſhing Eccleſiaſtical or Canon-Laws of Civil as well as Spiritual Authority, there the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, as to Civils, is in the King on the Right of his Soveraignty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; but what particular Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives ſhall accrue to Kings here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in reſtriction to the Churches
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66017:31"/>Liberties which ſhe had in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction from the State, will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on the Terms of the ſeveral Local Contracts and Coalitions; and therefore may be divers in diverſe places. and mutable in all; and ought not to be aſſerted of univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal and unchangeable Right on the account of meer Soveraignty ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply as ſuch; and if ſuch Contracts and Conditions violate no Divine Fundamentals, they are innocent, and perhaps alſo may be expedient; but if the Divine Tenures be broken down by them, no Man can ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them; and therefore when Laws of dubious or ſuſpicious Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation (as to Form of Words) are ſtrained, or perverted from the firſt fair Proſpects and Intentions of their Legiſlators to ill and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Purpoſes, as we cannot but abominate ſuch perverſions, ſo we cannot magnifie the Laws, that under ſuch deficiencies may be wreſted from the oppoſing to the doing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:66017:31"/>evil; in which caſe, tho' there is no reaſon to deſire a total abolition, yet Religion will force a Man to wiſh for a temper and ſecure Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>And thus you have the intimate Senſe and Soul herein, of the meaneſt of Gods Miniſters, in the Service of Gods Church; who (kind, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, Sir) is alſo particularly</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Kilmington,</hi>
                  <lb/>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 5.<lb/> 1697/8</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your obliged Servant, <hi>S. Hill.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
